After a two week trial, a Wisconsin jury acquitted Kyle Rittenhouse
在经过两周的审判之后，Wisconsin陪审团裁定Kyle Rittenhouse无罪并当庭释放。
for shooting three people, killing two during a racial justice protest in Kenosha.
其曾在Kenosha的一次种族平等的抗议活动中开枪致2死1伤。
At the time Rittenhouse was a 17 year old from Illinois
案发时，Rittenhouse是一名来自伊利诺伊的17岁少年。
who traveled to Kenosha after right-wing
在右翼社交媒体的号召下，
social media accounts called on people
Rittenhouse来到Kenosha市以保护
to protect the city from riots.
这座城市免受暴徒的破坏。
I am an EMT, if you are injured come to me.
我是名急救人员，如果你受伤了就到我这儿来。
Rittenhouse acted in the midst of a chaotic protest
Rittenhouse在这场骚乱中跑前跑后，其中参与者
where many people were legally carrying guns.
不乏众多合法持枪人员。
Bystander video showed that the three men
旁观者拍摄的视频显示被Rittenhouse用枪
that Rittenhouse shot had been in confrontations with him.
击中的三个人曾与其发生过对峙。
Rittenhouse has now been found not guilty on all six counts,
因其当天的行为，Rittenhouse 一共被指控了6项罪名，
arising from his conduct that day.
而今，这6项指控均被裁定无效，（并被当庭释放）。
[Jury Member] We the jury, find the defendant
[陪审团人员] 我们陪审团，认定被告人
Kyle H. Rittenhouse not guilty.
Kyle H. Rittenhouse 无罪。
So what happened at the Rittenhouse trial?
那么，在这场对Rittenhouse的审判中，到底发生了什么呢？
Why did the jury conclude that he was not guilty?
为什么陪审团最终给出他无罪的结论呢？
Is it a travesty of justice or a defensible outcome?
这是对正义的歪曲吗？或者这是一个可辩护的结果？
(light music)
（轻音乐）
There's no dispute that Rittenhouse killed two men
有一点是无争议的，那就是Rittenhouse枪杀2人
and injured a third, but as we talk about often
伤1人，但是正如我们频道经常说的那样，
on this channel, that's not the end of the analysis.
这不是对案件分析的结尾，
And here it was only the beginning.
恰恰是开始分析的地方。
Many people thought that when Kyle Rittenhouse
许多人认为，当Kyle Rittenhouse
admitted on the stand that he intentionally use deadly force
在法庭上承认他有意使用了致命武器
on Rosenbaum and Huber, that was a huge tactical blunder.
来对付Rosenbaum和Huber，是一种策略上的重大失误。
But intentional use of deadly force
但是，有意使用致命武器
is exactly the thing that is privileged
恰好是此类案件能够
when you meet the requirements of self-defense.
以正当防卫进行辩护的必要条件。
And this case hinged on whether self-defense applied or not.
因此，这起案件关键点是：正当防卫是否适用。
And more so than most self-defense cases,
而相比于大多数的自卫案件，(本案)更是如此。
this case turned on the nuances
本案揭示了自卫法与
of both self-defense law and criminal procedure.
刑事诉讼程序之间的细微差别。
It's not surprising to me that both sides
我并不惊讶于当事双方
got lots of stuff legally wrong.
都有很多不合法的行为存在。
So let's talk about the law of self-defense in Wisconsin,
那我们先来看一下Wisconsin州关于自卫的法律规定，
because every state has different self-defense laws.
因为每个州的自卫法律都有些差别。
And in Wisconsin, self-defense like many other states,
不过Wisconsin关于自卫的规定与其他许多州相同，
is an affirmative defense.
(在法庭上)是一种积极性抗辩。
In other words, the defendant has the burden
也就是说，辩护方承担
of producing some evidence.
提交证据的责任。
They must put forth some evidence
他们必须提交一些证据以使
from which a jury can find that self-defense applied.
陪审团认为自卫的条件适用于本案。
This is generally called the burden of production.
通常来说，这被称为举证责任。
But then, once the defense has made
届时，一旦辩方履行了
this relatively minimal burden,
这种相对较小的责任之后，
the burden of proof then returns to the prosecution,
证明责任的重担就落到了控方这里，
which must disprove self-defense beyond a reasonable doubt,
控方必须无可置疑的推翻自卫适用的结论，
which is the highest standard in all of law.
这在所有的法律案件中是最高水平的标准。
Now, every state has a self-defense law
现在，每个州都有自己的自卫法规，
that basically says a person who is not the aggressor
基本上都是说：若一个人不是冲突挑衅者，
is justified in using deadly force
在面对对方的攻击时，如果他合理的认为
against an adversary when he or she reasonably believes
他的生命和身体健康
that they're in imminent danger
即将处于危险中时，
of death or serious bodily injury.
他有权利使用致命武器进行防卫。
Now jurors aren't lawyers.
由于陪审员不是律师，
So juries receive jury instructions that include
因此，陪审团会收到所有判案时
all the law that they will need to decide a case,
需要参照的法律指引，
hopefully written in plain English.
希望这些指引是用白话文写的（与专业词汇描述相比）。
The lawyers and the judge fight over the jury instructions,
律师和法官就这些指引进行辩论，
which will be the only law that the jurors receive
对于陪审团而言，这些法律指引是他们
in that particular case.
判案的唯一依据。
Now it is supposed to accurately summarize
我们可以认为陪审团用到的
the law that the jurors are applying.
法律指引被准确的加以概括总结。
And as you can imagine,
自然地，你也能想象到
the language of the jury instructions
这些陪审团指引在语言上如何描述
is extremely important.
是非常重要的。
The Rittenhouse jury instructions
Rittenhouse案陪审团使用的法律指引
summarize the requirements for self-defense in Wisconsin as
将Wisconsin州法律中正当防卫的条件总结为：
"the defendant believed that there was an actual
“1）被告坚信自己即将遭受实际的
or imminent unlawful interference with the defendant's person.
非法的侵害；
And the defendant believed that the amount of force
2）并且为了防止或者终止这种侵害，
the defendant used or threatened to use
被告认为有必要使用或威胁使用
was necessary to prevent or terminate the interference
一定程度的暴力；
and the defendant's beliefs were reasonable.
3）并且被告在当时情形下的认知是合理的。
The defendant may intentionally use force,
被告可以有意的使用那些
which is intended or likely to cause death
可能造成他人死亡或重大人身伤害
or great bodily harm only if the defendant
的武器，（前提是）只要被告
reasonably believed that the force used was necessary
合理的认为必须采取这样的暴力行为
to prevent death or great bodily harm to himself."
才能防止自身的死亡或重大伤害。”
Now, in a situation like this,
现在我想说，在这样的情况下，
a reasonable belief doesn't mean true.
一种合理的认知并不意味着是正确的。
One can have a reasonable belief, but still be mistaken.
你可以有个合理的看法，但依然是错的。
Reasonableness is determined from the standpoint
合理性是由被告
of the defendant in the situation at issue,
当时的立场决定的，
not after the fact.
而不是事后诸葛。
And as an aside, the law of self-defense
顺便说一句，自卫法
gets slightly more complicated when you're applying it
对于各种蓄意谋杀和过失杀人案件的
to different varieties of homicide and manslaughter,
适用规定会更复杂些，
because the mental state required
因为对于每种案件，其要求
is different for each of those offenses.
的精神状态有所不同。
But you can read the jury instructions themselves
但是，你可以阅读一下陪审团指引
and see how the court modified the general rules
看看法庭是如何将自卫法的一般性规定
that apply to self-defense to apply to each
进行修改，以适用于本案中
of the different charges in this case.
不同的罪名指控。
It's all written down in relatively plain English,
这些都是用相对易懂的白话文写的，
and it's worthwhile.
并且值得你看看，
You might be on a jury someday,
因为你某天可能成为一名陪审员，
and you might be faced with similar jury instructions.
到时你也会收到类似的法律指引。
Now, Wisconsin doesn't have what's called a duty to retreat.
当前，Wisconsin并不要求逃跑义务，
In other words, Wisconsin law doesn't require someone
换句话说，Wisconsin州的法律并不要求：受害者
whose life is in danger to exercise all opportunities
面临生命危险时必须要先采取各种途径尝试逃离，
to flee before resorting to deadly force.
否则不能使用致命武器进行自卫反击。
But, jurors can consider whether someone
但是，陪审人员可以将受害者是否
tried to move away from danger,
尝试过逃离现场这一点
as they assess the reasonableness of a self-defense claim.
来作为评估正当防卫成立的合理性。
Juries are still allowed to consider
陪审团也可以考虑
whether the defendant had an opportunity to retreat
被告是否有机会逃离现场
to determine whether or not it was necessary
来决定其是否有必要
to use deadly force in self-defense.
使用致命武器进行自卫反击。
And Wisconsin law doesn't quite go as far
当然，Wisconsin州的法律也并没有
as stand your ground states,
极端到毫不退让的程度，
which remove any consideration of deescalating or fleeing
这样的规定允许受害者在使用致命武器反击之前
before resorting to deadly force.
无需考虑任何的妥协或逃离。
However, as we'll talk about later,
然而，正如我们稍后要讨论的，
Wisconsin does have a duty to retreat
Wisconsin州确实有一种情况要求逃跑义务：
where the person provokes the attack against them.
当冲突挑衅者自己（反过来）受到了威胁。
Now at common law, a majority of jurisdictions
在普通法中，多数州的法律法规
require a duty to retreat before being allowed to engage
要求在使用致命武器之前
in deadly force in self-defense.
必须要先履行逃跑义务。
But today, a duty to retreat is required
但是现在，只有少数州的法律
in only a minority of US states.
要求这一逃跑义务。
Here is a duty to retreat instruction from Massachusetts.
Massachusetts州关于逃跑义务的规定如下：
Quote, "a person cannot lawfully act in self-defense
“一个人在穷尽完所有合理的逃生途径之前
unless he or she has exhausted
不能诉诸于暴力（对挑衅者）
all other reasonable alternatives before resorting to force.
进行自卫反击。
A person may use physical force in self-defense
一个人只有在他或她在当时
only if he or she could not get out of the situation
无法通过任何有效且合理的途径逃离现场时
in some other way that was available
才可以使用物理的力量
and reasonable at the time.
进行自卫反击。
The Commonwealth, that is the state of Massachusetts,
Massachusetts州（检方）
may prove the defendant did not act in self-defense
需无可置疑的证明
by proving beyond a reasonable doubt
被告在诉诸暴力之前
that the defendant resorted to force
没有使用合理有效
without using avenues of escape
且不会置其于更危险境地的逃生途径，
that were reasonably available and which could not
从而使正当防卫的
have exposed the defendant to further danger."
辩护不成立。”
Again, that's the law of Massachusetts
再声明一次，那是Massachusetts州的法律，
and it's not the law of Wisconsin.
不是Wisconsin州的。
And it should go without saying that the Kenosha jury
并且无需多说，Kenosha陪审团
was applying the law of Wisconsin at the time.
肯定依据的是Wisconsin州的法律。
And we'll talk about the implications
接下来，我们就讨论一下
of this particular aspect of Wisconsin law in a second.
Wisconsin州法律中这种特殊情况的含义。
But the final nuance of self-defense at issue
在正当防卫的争论中，最终的差别点
is that of provocation.
在于（被告是否进行了）挑衅。
A person who provokes an attack
冲突的挑衅者
cannot claim legal self-defense.
不能声称自己是正当防卫，
But it's more complicated than just that.
当然实际情况更复杂些。
The Wisconsin law on provocation states,
Wisconsin州法对于挑衅方规定：
"a person who engages in unlawful conduct
“一个人因其某种非法行为
of a type likely to provoke others to attack him or her,
可能诱使他人对其进行反击，
and thereby does provoke an attack
并且（在非法行为后）确实引发了他人的反击，
is not entitled to claim the privilege of self-defense
（那么，）这个人对此类反击无权声称
against such attack, except when the attack which ensues
正当防卫，除非这样的反击
is of a type causing the person engaging
使得非法行为人
in the unlawful conduct to reasonably believe
合理的认为
that he or she is an imminent danger
他或她即将遭受死亡的威胁
of death or great bodily harm."
或重大人身伤害（才可进行正当防卫）。”
Okay, so let's break down this law on provocation,
OK，我们来拆解一下法律中关于挑衅的规定：
which is an exception to the exception of self-defense,
如果正当防卫算作一种允许使用致命武器对付他人的例外，
which is an exception to the ability
那么允许挑衅者使用正当防卫
to use deadly force against someone.
就是一种例外中的例外。
So let's say you engage in unlawful conduct
所以我们说当你进行某种非法行为
likely to provoke others,
而可能导致他人反击时，
well, then you can't claim self-defense.
你无权声称正当防卫。
Except that you can, if your provocation causes others
但如果你的挑衅行为致使对方使用
to use effectively deadly force against you.
有效的致命武器对付你时，你就可以。
Now we'll get back to this in a second,
稍后我们还会说回这一点，
but the law continues.
法律继续说到，
In such a case where the provoked attacker
在反击者使用致命武器
uses deadly force against the provoker,
对付挑衅者的情况下，
the person engaging in the unlawful conduct
非法行为人（即挑衅者）
is privileged to act in self-defense,
有权进行正当防卫，
but the person is not privileged
但是挑衅者无权
to resort to the use of force
使用可能造成反击者死亡
intended or likely to cause death to the person's assailant,
的暴力武器（进行自卫），
unless the person reasonably believes that he or she
除非挑衅者合理的认为他或她
has exhausted every other reasonable means
已经穷尽了所有的逃离途径，以及尝试了
to escape from or otherwise avoid death or great bodily harm
各种避免生命死亡
at the hands of his or her assailant.
或重大人身伤害的方式。
So here, you only get to use deadly force
所以此种情况下，你能使用致命武器
to resist the deadly force that you provoked
对抗你挑起的威胁的唯一
if you exercise a duty to retreat.
条件是你履行了逃跑义务。
Wisconsin law stipulates that the provocateur
Wisconsin州的法律规定，冲突挑衅者
must attempt every other reasonable option to escape,
必须在尝试了各种逃离，
avoid, or prevent the attack
避免或预防这种反击的途径之后
before resorting to deadly force if they were the ones
才能诉诸于致命武器
that provoked the secondary attack.
对抗其本人挑起的二次反击。
Now we'll talk about the general law of self-defense
现在我们就来讨论一下自卫法的一般条文
and whether it applies under the factual circumstances
及其对接下来要看到的事实情况
as we know them in a second.
是否适用。
But first I want to talk about the exception of provocation
但是首先我想先讨论一下挑衅这种情况的特例，
because a number of people believe
因为有很多人相信
that Kyle Rittenhouse provoked the attacks themselves,
Kyle Rittenhouse挑起了这些冲突从而受到攻击，
and therefore couldn't use the privilege of self-defense.
所以他不能进行正当防卫的辩护。
That by brandishing a firearm
在那样骚乱的现场，他却
or placing himself in this situation,
挎着一把枪晃来晃去,
he provoked the attack.
（很明显，）这种行为挑起了冲突。
Now there's three issues here.
好，这儿有三点需要说明。
First, is there unlawful conduct?
首先，这里有违法行为吗？
Did Kyle Rittenhouse engage in unlawful conduct
Kyle Rittenhouse是否存在挑起冲突的
that could constitute provocation
违法行为
and therefore prevent the defense of self-defense?
而使其无法进行自我防卫？
Well, Judge Schroeder granted defense motions to dismiss
嗯，Schroeder法官同意了辩方提出的撤销
the two misdemeanor charges against Rittenhouse.
针对Rittenhouse的两项轻罪指控的动议。
I think a lot of people put too much emphasis
我感觉许多人太关注
on those lesser included offenses.
在那些较轻的罪行上。
The charges were for possessing
（被撤销的两项指控）分别是
a dangerous weapon as a minor,
未成年携带致命武器
and a misdemeanor charge for breaking curfew.
以及违反宵禁这一轻罪。
And arguably, Wisconsin law has an exception
按理说，Wisconsin州有个例外
that allows miners to possess shotguns and rifles,
即允许未成年携带猎枪和步枪，
as long as they're not short barreled.
只要这些枪不是短桶的。
But more importantly, provocation requires
更重要的是，（法律上的）挑衅行为
unlawful conduct of a type likely to provoke others.
要求是会激怒他人的非法行为。
Now, even if those two lesser included charges had stuck,
所以，即使那两项轻罪指控保留了下来，
they might not have been sufficient
也不足以
to rise to the level of provocation.
达到“挑衅行为”的标准。
Mainly because Wisconsin is an open carry state.
主要因为Wisconsin州允许公开携带枪支。
Mere open carry of a firearm is A, not unlawful.
仅仅公开持枪，一不违法，
And B, possibly not the type
二也不太可能算是一种
likely to lead to provoking others.
挑衅他人的行为。
Now I'm oversimplifying here.
接下来，我就简单来说了。
This is a highly fact-specific analysis,
虽然这是高度基于特定事实的分析，
but it's not unreasonable that someone might not find
但是有人也会发现（公然）
that the gun possession, quad gun possession
持枪（或持四管枪）会激怒他人
didn't lead to provocation.
也不是不无道理。
Think about it, is it the possession of the gun
试想一下，究竟是持有枪支
that provokes the attack?
挑起了冲突，
Or is it the possession of a gun by a minor
还是未成年持枪，
or possession of a gun that crossed state lines
或者携枪跨越州境
that leads to someone provoking an attack?
引起了冲突的激化呢？
If you think it's the former, well, that's not illegal.
如果你认为是前者，然而那并不违法。
And the latter probably doesn't provoke an attack.
而后者也不太可能会挑起冲突。
No one says, oh, the reason I'm attacking you
没人会说，哦，我攻击你的原因是：
is that you're a minor with a firearm,
你是个持枪的未成年人员，
not that you're carrying a firearm in the first place.
而不是因为你持枪这个行为。
And additionally, breaking curfew
并且违反宵禁
probably couldn't be the requisite predicate
也不可能是挑起冲突的前提
because lots of people were breaking curfew
因为许多人都违反了宵禁但并没有
and it wasn't leading to mass provocation.
引起大规模的冲突激化。
Now, it's a closer call when you consider Rittenhouse
当你认为Rittenhouse
admitted that he pointed his gun at the victims
承认他举着枪瞄准了受害者
and claimed that when he was pointing his gun,
并且声称他拿枪对准他人不算是一种
it wasn't a dangerous provocation.
危险的挑衅，这种想法就更不太好说过去了。
Now you could argue that pointing your gun at someone
你也许会争论拿枪对准他人
is assault or misuse of a firearm,
就是一种攻击或者滥用武器，
but that probably doesn't work
但这种说法也可能说不过去，
if the reason that you're pointing the gun
（因为）如果拿枪对准
at someone in the first place
他人的最初原因
is for the purposes of self-defense.
是为了正当防卫。
And in fact, there are Wisconsin cases to this effect.
事实上，Wisconsin对此类案件是有过先例的。
Though, on the other other hand,
而另一方面，
Wisconsin courts have an interesting history
Wisconsin州法院有个有意思的先例
in analyzing the provocation exception.
就是对（自卫中）挑衅例外情况的分析。
For example, in a 1975 Wisconsin Supreme Court case,
例如一起1975年Wisconsin高等法院的案件：
the court held that the defendant was a provocateur
（这起案件中，）因被告公然将一把枪带回客栈
by virtue of openly bringing a gun into a tavern.
而被法庭认定“挑衅行为”成立。
The Wisconsin Supreme Court held quote,
Wisconsin高等法院的记录如下：
"the defendant himself testified that after being slapped,
“被告本人供认在被扇了耳光之后，
he went out to his car, got his shotgun,
他跑到车内，取出手枪，
loaded it and returned to the tavern.
上了膛并返回客栈。
As he was entering the tavern,
在他进入客栈时，
he was grabbed from the side by someone
他被人从侧面抓住
and he pushed that person away.
并且他推开了那个人。
He saw Freddy Jones start toward him
他看到了Freddy Jones面向他
and he started shooting.
并开枪射击。
He stopped after four shots
他连发了四枪，并在
and after Jones was out of sight.
Jones逃跑了之后停了下来。”
The defendant requests that the court
被告方请求法院
grant him a new trial in the interest of justice.
为了正义而准许再次审判。
We find no merit to this contention.
我们发现没有这个必要
When the defendant left the tavern,
当被告离开了客栈，
got his shotgun out of the trunk,
从车中取出枪支，
loaded it and returned to the tavern,
上膛并返回客栈，
he became the provoker."
他此时成了一名挑衅者。”
Additionally, there is an 1883
此外，还有一起1883年
Wisconsin Supreme Court case that says,
Wisconsin州高等法院的案例声明：
quote, "if one points a loaded gun at another,
“如果一个人将一把上膛的枪对准他人，
and the other grapples with him to prevent the shooting
第三人与其发生扯拽并试图阻止其开枪，
and is shot, it is murder."
并且他还是开枪了，这就是谋杀。”
And this is especially important
这一点在本案Rittenhouse开枪
in the context of the Rittenhouse shooting.
的背景下尤其重要。
Even Rittenhouse's testimony seems to indicate
即使Rittenhouse的证词似乎表达了
that Rosenbaum didn't lunge at Rittenhouse
在他将枪瞄准Rosenbaum之前，Rosenbaum并
until he raised his gun at Rosenbaum.
没有朝他扑来。
And that the reason, or at least one of the reasons
而Kyle Rittenhouse射击Rosenbaum
that Kyle Rittenhouse shot Rosenbaum is that he feared
的原因（至少原因之一）是他担心
that Rosenbaum would take his gun away
Rosenbaum会夺走他手里的枪
and use it against him.
并用来对付他。
And we'll talk about that in a second.
我们接下来就讨论这一点。
And obviously, you'd have to run a provocation analysis
很显然，本案中每处Kyle Rittenhouse开枪的地方
in every instance where Kyle Rittenhouse used deadly force.
都要进行挑衅分析。
It's not a one size fits all.
仅仅分析一次无法适用所有情形。
You have to look at every instance individually.
你必须单独拆开来分析每一种情形。
And if the jury had found that there was
如果陪审团已经发现
nothing unlawful that led to provocation,
无任何非法行为或者
or if there were illegal things going on,
即使有非法行为
those weren't the ones that were leading to the provocation,
但并不是引起挑衅的行为，
their analysis to this exception
那他们对（本案中）挑衅行为的分析
probably would have ended there.
也就到此为止了。
And they would have found that provocation didn't apply.
他们发现挑衅行为并不成立。
It's only where there is provocation
仅当挑衅行为存在时，
do we get to the next questions.
我们才需要继续分析下面的问题。
But, assuming that that first hurdle had been met,
但是我们假定第一步满足了，
you'd get to the next one, imminent danger.
那接下来你就要分析“迫在眉睫的风险”这一点了。
Even when someone provokes an attack,
即使一个人挑起了冲突，
they can regain the right to use deadly force
当他合理的认为他即将遭遇生命死亡
where that person reasonably believes that he
或重大人身伤害，他也可以
is in imminent danger of death or great bodily harm.
重新具有使用致命武器的权利
And he may lawfully act in self-defense.
并合法的进行自卫反击。
Since this is essentially the same standard
由于本质上这种自卫
as self-defense in the first instance,
和原先的自卫有相同的标准，
given that the jury must have thought
鉴于陪审团一定认为
Kyle Rittenhouse acted in self-defense,
Kyle Rittenhouse在进行正当防卫，
they probably would have found that this exception
即使他们来分析这个问题，
to the exception, to the exception applied,
那么很可能也会发现这种例外中的例外情形
even if they got to this question.
也是适用的。
And so if they got over those two first hurdles,
所以如果他们跨过了这两道坎，
they then would have had to get over the third hurdle,
他们还将必须跨域第三道坎：
which is the duty to retreat.
逃跑义务。
That's the final issue in terms of
假定前两个条件都满足了，
whether provocation can apply,
那么是否挑衅情形成立就取决于
assuming the first two hurdles are met.
这最后的一个问题。
The third clause says that the person
这第三条款说挑起冲突的人
who provokes the attack cannot use or threaten force,
不能使用或威胁使用暴力，
unless he believes that he has exhausted
除非他认为他已经
all other opportunities to escape.
穷尽了所有其他逃生的可能。
If the jury got to this question,
如果陪审团真要考虑这个问题，
they could have felt that he had no choice
他们可能已经觉得在那样的情形下
under the circumstances, we don't know.
他别无选择，当然我们不知道（陪审团会怎么认为）。
And one of the prior issues might have precluded
并且即使考虑到这一步，
even getting to this question.
之前的一个问题已经被排除了。
But if the jury did reach this question,
但如果陪审团确实在考虑这个问题，
then they felt that Kyle Rittenhouse
那他们认为Kyle Rittenhouse
either had no opportunity to escape
要么没有机会逃跑，
or had exhausted all of those opportunities.
要么穷尽了所有逃生的可能。
If that's the case, whether Wisconsin had
如果真是这样，不管Wisconsin州的法律是否有
a general duty to retreat might not have changed
一般意义上逃跑义务的规定也不会
the overall outcome here anyway.
改变本案最终的判决结果。
Anyone who says that this is a simple case of self-defense
有人说这就是个简单的自卫案件
or that it's cut and dry is definitely wrong.
或者就这么回事，这肯定是不对的。
But so far, we've talked about the exception
到目前为止，我们已经讨论了自卫例外中的
to the exception, that is provocation.
例外情形，即挑衅者的自卫权。
Let's now talk about whether the original exception,
下面我们讨论一下原始的例外，
self-defense, applied or could reasonably have applied
正当防卫是否在这起特殊案件中适用，或者
in this particular case.
适用的是否有道理。
Let's talk about the facts as we know them from the trial.
我们讨论一下法庭审判中呈现的事实。
Now, warning, these videos are graphic,
注意，这些视频都很形象，
but let's talk about what the relatively
但我们来讨论相对
uncontested testimony and these videos shows,
无争议的证词，并且这些视频显示：
Rittenhouse and his friend, Dominic Black
Rittenhouse和他的朋友Dominic Black
testified that they went to Kenosha
供认他们前往Kenosha
to protect a car dealership called Car Source.
去保护叫做Car Source的汽车经销商。
The two owners of the dealership told jurors
而经销商的两个老板告诉陪审团
that they never asked anyone to protect Car Source.
他们从没要求任何人去保护Car Source。
During the protest, a small group of 8 to 9 people
在抗议骚乱期间，有8，9个人的小人群
were gathered at the dealership.
聚集在那家车店门前。
Kyle Rittenhouse, that night,
那一晚，Kyle Rittenhouse
was separated from the rest of his group
跟他的群体走散了，
and jogged towards one of the Car Source parking lots.
然后（独自一人）朝着Car Source的其中一个停车场慢跑过去。
Kyle Rittenhouse apparently sees Joshua Ziminski
显然，Kyle Rittenhouse看到Joshua Ziminski
is nearby armed with a pistol.
在附近并带着一把枪。
Rittenhouse continues to run towards Car Source.
Rittenhouse 继续朝Car Source跑去。
Rosenbaum chases Kyle Rittenhouse.
Rosenbaum在后面追着 Kyle Rittenhouse，
Rosenbaum throws a plastic bag behind Kyle Rittenhouse,
并向Kyle Rittenhouse投掷塑料袋，
which lands on the ground.
塑料袋落到了地上。
A shot is fired from someone else about a hundred feet away.
（此时，）在一百英尺意外有人开了枪。
Kyle Rittenhouse turns around and stops
Kyle Rittenhous跑到了一处停了很多车的地方，
as he gets to some parked cars
转过身停了下来
and shoots the unarmed Rosenbaum four times
朝没有持枪的Rosenbaum连开四枪，
in quick succession, once in the back.
其中一发击中其背部。
(shots firing, people screaming)
人们大喊，有人开枪了
Kyle Rittenhouse then runs away from the scene.
Kyle Rittenhouse随后逃离了开枪现场。
A loose crowd starts to follow Kyle Rittenhouse.
松松散散的一群人开始追着Kyle Rittenhouse跑。
(man in crowd) That guy shot someone, get (beep).
（人群中喊道）就是那个家伙开枪打人了，抓住（脏话消音）。
Rittenhouse trips, falls to the ground,
（在被追逐下），Ritttenhouse摔倒在地，
sits up right and points his gun
立马坐起来并拿枪瞄准
at one person who backs away.
了一个人迫使其后退。
He shoots at a man who does sort of a half jump kick,
有个人大约半飞起朝他踢了上去，他于是开枪了，
but backs away after the shot.
那个人在枪响之后跑走了。
At roughly the same time,
几乎同时，
Anthony Huber hits Kyle Rittenhouse with a skateboard.
Anthony Huber拿着滑板向Kyle Rittenhouse抡去，
Rittenhouse fires a shot.
Rittenhouse就开枪射击了。
Huber picks up the skateboard and runs away.
Huber捡起滑板跑了。
Another shot is fired in either the direction
然后朝着Huber或Gaige Grosskreutz方向
of Huber or Gaige Grosskreutz.
又开了一枪。
Huber drops to the ground.
Huber倒在地上。
Grosskreutzthen puts his hands up while armed with a pistol.
Grosskreutzthen拿着一把手枪举起双手。
As he's making a move toward
在他进一步
or to the side of Rittenhouse,
朝Rittenhouse方向移动时，
Rittenhouse then fires at Grosskreutz
Rittenhouse朝Grosskreutz开枪射击，
hitting him once in the bicep.
其中一发打中了二头肌。
Now this is of course,
以上基本就是案件的经过，
a hopefully neutral oversimplification.
希望我是客观的进行了简要描述。
There are a lot of other facts.
当然还有很多其他的事实。
But at base, this is a confusing in-charge situation,
但本质上，即使有视频脚本为证，
even with video footage.
这也是一种让人困惑纠结的局面。
And it's not an easy case in either direction.
从哪个方面来看，这也不是一起显而易见的案子。
So was this self-defense?
这算是正当防卫吗？
You can look at those facts and see a murder.
就目前呈现的事实，你可以说这是谋杀，
You can look at those facts and find self-defense.
你也可以看到正当防卫。
Two diametrically opposed beliefs
两种截然不同的结论
can both be reasonable at the same time.
可以同时成立。
There are a ton of open questions here.
这里有很多（可讨论的）开放性问题，比如：
Was the use of force proportionate in every encounter?
每一次对峙中使用武器都合适吗？
Was the use of force reasonable in every encounter?
每一次对峙中使用武器都合理吗？
Did Rittenhouse provoke any of those reactions?
那些冲突行为是由Rittenhouse激化挑起的吗？
But the videos and testimonies show
那些视频和证词都显示
a chaotic situation and people acting quickly.
在当时混乱的情形，人们也都快速反应移动，
Now no blanket assertions can be made.
我们无法得到确定通用的结论。
You have to run the self-defense analysis
你必须针对每一次开枪事件
for each incident individually,
单独进行正当防卫（成立与否的）分析，
including the shots fired at the people
包括除射向Rosenbaum, Huber和Grosskreutz
that weren't Rosenbaum, Huber or Grosskreutz.
之外的开枪行为。
With the provocation argument aside,
我们先撇开关于挑衅的争论，
one might look at these incidents in question
单看这些事件本身
and decide that they were self-defense.
来决定其是否属于正当防卫。
After all in the latter two incidents,
毕竟在后面的两次冲突事件中，
Kyle Rittenhouse was fending off
Kyle Rittenhouse躲避了
what was arguably an attack with a skateboard
尚存争议的来自滑板的攻击
and in another, the man admitted
以及当事人承认他拿着一把
he drew a gun on Rittenhouse.
枪对准了Rittenhouse。
But one might also reasonably conclude
但是也有人可以合理的推论出
that one or more of these incidents
其中一个或更多次冲突
were not self-defense and were therefore murder.
不是自卫而是谋杀。
After all, in the first incidence,
毕竟，在第一起冲突中，
Rosenbaum, an unarmed man threw a bag of clothes
并未携枪的Rosenbaum朝Rittenhouse扔
at Rittenhouse, which didn't land anywhere near Rittenhouse,
了一个塑料袋并且落地处都离得Rittenhouse很远，
after which Rittenhouse points his gun at him.
之后Rittenhouse拿着枪对准了他。
And then Rosenbaum moves at Rittenhouse
而Rosenbaum还是朝着Rittenhouse跑去，
or apparently towards the gun,
或者很明显，是朝着枪跑去，
and Rittenhouse shoots him four times, once in the back.
于是Rittenhouse连开四枪，其中一枪击中其背部。
And yes, I'm aware of Rittenhouse's
是的，我知道Rittenhouse对冲突前
self-serving testimony about the preceding incidents.
的证词描述是有利于自己的。
What I'm saying is that reasonable minds can differ.
我想说的是理性的思维可以是不同的。
And Rittenhouse also shoots at, but misses,
Rittenhouse同样也射击了曾半飞起
the unarmed jump-kick man.
踢他的无枪男，但没射中。
And latter incidents involving Grosskreutz and Huber
之后发生了涉及Grosskreutz和Huber的枪击事件，
happened perhaps a few hundred feet away
而几十辆警车也许就停在
from several dozen police officers.
数百英尺之外。
It's not surprising that the people who pursued Rittenhouse
追着Rittenhouse跑的人们认为是他主动开枪射击
thought he was an active shooter who needed to be stopped.
并应被制止的想法并不让人意外。
But the only question in this particular case
但是在这起特殊的案件中唯一的问题是
was whether Rittenhouse's actions
是否Rittenhouse的反应行为
could possibly have been reasonable.
可能是合理的。
Because remember, the standard is that
请记住，因为判定标准是
the jury must find that there is no reasonable doubts
陪审团必须是没有任何怀疑得认为
that it wasn't self-defense.
这不是正当防卫。
It's possible, if not probable,
也许不是十分可能，但有一定可能的是
that both Rittenhouse and the people he killed
Rittenhouse和被他枪杀的人
were simultaneously acting in self-defense.
同时都在进行正当防卫。
The fog of war is a real thing.
战争迷雾是真实存在的。
Reasonable beliefs can be mistaken.
（主观上）有理由的相信也可能是错的
The jury was accurately, based on the law,
根据法律，陪审团准确的
told that they had to determine
说出他们必须根据当时的形式
whether Rittenhouse's belief was reasonable
来决定Rittenhouse当时的认知
based on the circumstances.
是否合理。
And this reminds me of the story
说到这儿倒让我想起
of Gabby Giffords and Joe Zamudio.
Gabby Giffords和Joe Zamudio的案子。
when Giffords was shot at a political rally,
在Tucson市的一场政治集会中，当Giffords被枪击中，
Joe Zamudio, who was legally armed,
合法持枪的Joe Zamudio
came running to help when he heard the gunfire
听到枪响立马跑过来帮忙，
that injured Gabby Giffords and killed six others in Tucson.
此集会中的枪击事件造成Gabby Giffords受伤和6人死亡。
By the time that Zamudio came to the scene,
当Zamudio到达现场时，
unarmed civilians had already tackled
无枪的市民已经制止
and disarmed the perpetrator.
并剥夺了行凶者的手枪。
Zamudio later said that in his confusion,
Zamudio后来说当时他很迷惑，
he was within seconds of shooting
就在几秒之内他开枪
one of the people that was helping, not the shooter himself.
打中了一名见义勇为者而不是歹徒。
This is an issue that champions of Rittenhouse
这是Rittenhouse的支持者
should grapple with.
应该面对的问题。
If Rosenbalm or Huber or Grosskreutz
如果是Rosenbalm 或 Huber 或 Grosskreutz
had killed Kyle Rittenhouse, they might've been justified
杀了Kyle Rittenhouse，他们可能也会
in using self-defense under the law.
基于法律做正当防卫的辩护。
Again, reasonable minds might differ on this.
再声明一次，理性的思维在这种情况下可能是不同的。
But any system that incentivizes rule
任何体制的规则都是
by the last person standing,
由最后活着的人激励巩固，
that is killing the only person
那就是说把那个可能
who might dispute your claim of self-defense.
阻碍你声称自卫的人杀掉吧。
That seems well suboptimal.
这样看起来不是最地道的。
It's at this point, that my notes simply say,
此时此刻，我的笔记上简单的写着
vigilantism is bad.
义务警员制是不好的。
And I stand by that.
我还是坚持这一点。
I also worry that that is becoming a controversial position.
我也担心案子正变成有争议的局面。
Net net bringing guns to a protest is bad.
毕竟，持枪来到抗议现场是不好的。
Anyone that brings it, not just Kyle Rittenhouse.
我不单单说Kyle Rittenhouse，而是所有人。
But there's a large strain of people that simply say
还有大量的人简单认为
that Kyle Rittenhouse shouldn't have been there.
Kyle Rittenhouse本就不应该来这儿。
And that's the reason that he can't use self-defense.
这就是他不能进行自卫辩护的原因。
And by most accounts,
在大多数情况下，
Kyle Rittenhouse meets the definition of a vigilante.
Kyle Rittenhouse可以算是一名义务警员。
But whether Kyle Rittenhouse should have been there
但是Kyle Rittenhouse是否应该出现在那儿
in the first place isn't relevant to the questions
这一问题与他
of whether he legally met the definition
是否能合法的进行
of self-defense in the first place.
正当防卫辩护并不相关。
Just simply possessing a gun by itself,
仅仅持有枪支
doesn't prevent the application of self-defense.
也不能阻止正当防卫的成立。
And there are of course, larger social issues here as well.
当然，这里也有更大意义上的社会问题。
Many have claimed that it would have been impossible
许多人说如果是一个黑人
for a black person to kill two people,
枪杀了两个人，伤了一人
injured a third and fire at a fourth
并向第四人开了枪，那么他一定不可能
and live to walk away from the scene as Rittenhouse did,
像Rittenhouse那样被判无罪，
And then of course, to be found, not guilty.
并走出法庭。
And we can probably evaluate whether this is true or not.
那我们来评估一下这样说对不对。
One way to look at this is by studying the data
一个途径是我们来研究一下
on how jury's perceive self-defense.
陪审团是如何判定正当防卫方面的数据。
a study by John Roman found that homicides
John Roman的一份研究指出
with a white perpetrator and a black victim
白人杀害黑人
are 10 times more likely to be ruled justified
被判无罪的案件数量
than cases with a black perpetrator and a white victim.
是黑人杀害白人的10倍
And the gap is larger in states with stand your ground laws.
并且在有毫不退让法的州，这个差距更大。
And after accounting for a variety of confounding factors,
再算上一些混杂的因素，
such as whether the victim and perpetrator were strangers,
比如被害人和施害者是否认识等，
the gap is smaller, but still significant.
（虽然）这个差距会变小一点，但依然很大。
Cases with a white perpetrator and black victim
白人杀害黑人
are 281% more likely to be ruled justified
与黑人杀害白人相比，
than cases with a black perpetrator and white victim.
前者有281%的概率被判定为合法。
But systemic issues like that weren't on trial here.
但像这种系统性问题不会被法庭审判。
You don't adjudicate those kinds of systemic issues
你不会在一个单独的刑事法庭
in a criminal court of one individual.
上裁定那种系统性问题。
The issue is whether Kyle Rittenhouse
（法庭审判的是）Kyle Rittenhouse
engaged in self-defense or more specifically,
的行为是否是正当防卫，或者更确切的说，
whether the prosecution disproved the possibility
控方是否能证明他不具备
that he used self-defense.
自卫的任何可能。
And for what it's worth, there are lots of people
无论如何，还是有许多人
who think that Kyle Rittenhouse's actions
认为Kyle Rittenhouse的行为
were not self-defense.
不是正当防卫。
There are lots of other reasonable people
（同时，也）有很多理性的人
who think that Kyle Rittenhouse's actions were self-defense.
认为Kyle Rittenhouse的行为是正当防卫。
Now I doubt all of those people in both of those groups
我怀疑两方的人是否像Kenosha的陪审团那样
watched 100% of the trial then spent days
全程100%观看了法庭审判，
pouring over the jury instructions
然后花费几天的时间
like the Kenosha jury did.
思考发给陪审团的法律指引。
But the thing is, if reasonable people
问题是，如果一些理性的人
really could conclude that this was self-defense,
真的能得出正当防卫的结论，
then it means that the prosecution
那么这就意味着控方
didn't prove self-defense beyond a reasonable doubt.
未能毫无置疑的证明这不是正当防卫。
That's the definition of reasonable doubt.
这算是合理怀疑的含义。
Now that being said, an acquittal doesn't mean
话虽如此，Kyle Rittenhouse未被定罪但并不意味着
that Kyle Rittenhouse didn't do it.
他没有做这件事。
It doesn't mean that what Kyle Rittenhouse did was right.
（同时，）也并不意味着Kyle Rittenhouse这样做就是对的。
And the pathology of Kyle Rittenhouse's
而关于Kyle Rittenhouse圣徒言行的
hagiography is another issue entirely.
反常完全是另外一个问题了。
And it certainly doesn't mean that he did nothing wrong.
当然，这也并不意味着他什么都没做错。
It just means the jury didn't think
只能说明陪审团并不认为
that the prosecution proved self-defense
控方毫无置疑的证明了
beyond a reasonable doubt.
正当防卫不成立。
And while you can't necessarily infer it
尽管你不一定能从陪审团的决定
from the jury's decision, it might be the case
推断出上面的结论，但这可以说明
that Kyle Rittenhouse did nothing legally wrong.
在法律上Kyle Rittenhouse并没有做错什么。
But under the most favorable interpretations of the facts,
但是对事实做最有利的解释，
Kyle Rittenhouse brought gasoline to a match party
Kyle Rittenhouse带着汽油去参加火柴派对
and people are now dead as a result.
结果是人全死了。
He made a bad situation worse.
他的行为使不好的的情形变的更糟。
And let's face it, if someone uses non-deadly force
就事实来说，如果有人使用非致命武器
against you while you are carrying a gun,
挑衅身上带枪的你，
it's more likely to turn deadly.
结果是很可能对方丧命。
Rosenbaum, jump-kick man and arguably, Huber,
Rosenbaum, jump-kick man和有些争议的Huber
used non-deadly force,
使用的是非致命武器,
which would not in the abstract
理论上这种武器让人有理由相信
trigger a reasonable belief of imminent harm,
不会带来立即的伤害，
which is not to say that unarmed people
当然，这也不是说没带武器的人
can't exercise deadly force or create a reasonable belief
就不能致人死地或者造成明显的
of eminent, deadly harm,they absolutely can.
致命伤害，他们绝对可以。
Indeed, it appears that the jury
事实上看起来陪审团
believed Rittenhouse's testimony
采信了Rittenhouse的证词：
that they were going for his gun
他们看准了他的枪，
or grabbed his gun in an attempt to take his gun
或者要抓住他的枪夺过来
and use it against him.
并对付他。
And in a huge stretch, in Rittenhouse's speculation,
并且就Rittenhouse的更广泛的推测而言，
take his gun and use it against others.
他们夺了他的枪之后还会危及其他人。
Now, those arguing that, but for Kyle Rittenhouse,
那些认为要不是Kyle Rittenhouse
being present with his gun,
带着枪来
these shootings wouldn't have happened are right.
枪击也不会发生的想法是对的。
However, but for causation,
然而，这种“要不是”的因果问题，
or what we call sine qua non causation,
或者我们称其为必要条件，
it doesn't rise to the level of guilt
根本达不到“毫无置疑”
beyond a reasonable doubt.
判其有罪的水平。
It's necessary for a conviction, but it's not sufficient.
这对犯罪行为是必要的，但不是充分的。
Now I've seen lots of people say, quote,
我看到过很多人说：
"the jury reached the right verdict."
“陪审团作出了正确的裁决。”
Now there is a strong version
对于这个表述有一个强版本
and a weak version of that statement.
和弱版本。
The weak version is that the jury was correct
弱版本是说陪审团对Kyle Rittenhouse
to find that there was reasonable doubt
不是正当防卫的论点
that Kyle Rittenhouse didn't use self-defense.
持有一些合理的怀疑。
However, the strong version is that the jury
而强版本则说陪审团
proactively found him innocent or even a hero.
毫无怀疑的认定他是无辜的，甚至是一名英雄。
But assuming we're going with the weak version,
设想我们采用弱版本的说法，
it's entirely possible that the jury verdict
那么陪审团完全可能是
accurately reflects the law of Wisconsin.
准确的遵照Wisconsin州的法律作出的裁决。
I've never seen a politician run on a platform
我从来没见过一个政客
of installing a duty to retreat in the law.
要给法律加上逃跑义务。
If Wisconsin had a duty to retreat,
如果Wisconsin规定了逃跑义务，
the outcome of this case,
那么此案的结果
very well might've been different.
非常有可能就不一样了。
Stated differently, if this had occurred in Massachusetts,
换句话说，如果此案发生在Massachusetts州，
the law could have militated a different result.
该州的法律可能产生不同的结果。
Though, admittedly, maybe reasonable minds
然而还是得承认，到时理性的人们
might differ on that as well.
对此案也会产生分歧。
Maybe Kyle Rittenhouse retreated
也许Kyle Rittenhouse穷尽了
at every possible opportunity.
所有可能逃生的机会。
But I will leave it to you and by proxy, your politicians,
那这（添加逃跑义务）究竟是好还是坏，我就
as to whether that is a good thing or a bad thing.
留给你和代理你的政客决定吧。
Though, I'll point out that for those
然而，我要指出对于那些
that are happy that Kyle Rittenhouse was found not guilty,
乐见Kyle Rittenhouse无罪的人，
they should recognize that logically,
他们应该意识到，逻辑上讲，
they should also be in favor of an alternate reality
他们也乐见另外一种事实的发生：
where Gaige Grosskreutz shot and killed Kyle Rittenhouse.
Gaige Grosskreutz用枪射杀了Kyle Rittenhouse。
And remember, if you think that
记住，如果你认为
Rosenbaum, Huber or Grosskreutz
Rosenbaum, Huber或者Grosskreutz
all provoked a response from Kyle Rittenhouse,
挑衅了Kyle Rittenhouse而致使
Rittenhouse's use of deadly force
Rittenhouse使用了致命武器，
probably gave them the right to use deadly force right back
那么在相同的法律下，这也给了他们三人使用
under the same laws.
致命武器回击的权利。
Under current Wisconsin law, if Kyle Rittenhouse
在Wisconsin当前的法律下，如果Kyle Rittenhouse
is not guilty, by reason of self-defense,
因为正当防卫无罪，
Gaige Grosskreutz would also have been not guilty
那么若是Gaige Grosskreutz枪杀了Kyle Rittenhouse，
if he had shot and killed Kyle Rittenhouse.
那他也可能会是无罪的。
And keep in mind that in this scenario,
记住在这种情况下，
Kyle Rittenhouse is dead and it would have been
Kyle Rittenhouse死了，
Grosskreutz setting the narrative.
是Grosskreutz在陈述这件事。
And to the extent that you think Grosskreutz
你可以想象到Grosskreutz
would have crafted his testimony to support
会精心遣造他的证词来支持
an argument of self-defense.
他做正当防卫的辩护。
Then consider that Kyle Rittenhouse probably crafted
而现在是Kyle Rittenhouse，同样的，他很可能
his story in exactly the same way.
也好好准备了他的叙事。
So the ultimate takeaway here
所以最终的要点是
is that these incidents are murky at best.
这些冲突事件充其量都是模糊不清的。
Occurred in a jurisdiction with very broad
在一个有着非常宽泛的
self-defense and firearm laws，
自卫和携枪法律的州，
the prosecution had a very high standard to meet.
控方（要想胜诉）是要满足很高标准的。
And while we didn't cover it in this video,
虽然我在本视频中没有提到，
the defendant put on a very good defense.
但（其实）辩方的表现也非常出色。
The rest I will leave to you.
（好，）其余的分析我就留给你了。
Now, if you'd like to watch something legal,
现在如果你喜欢看一下法律的东西，
that's much more lighthearted,
并且要更轻松一些的，
I'd recommend my mini documentary, "Bad Law Words Good"
那我推荐我的迷你纪录片, “法劣词良”，
where I explore all of the most common legal
在这些记录片中，我会探索所有最常见的法律
and linguistic comments that people throw around
和语言评论，这些评论都是人们在日常生活中
in everyday life incorrectly.
到处用且用的不对。
It is a hilarious and educational romp
（视频中，我会）通过法律误解，
through legal misunderstandings, logical fallacies,
逻辑缺陷以及法律与秩序的荒诞事件，
and law and order parodies.
以一种既幽默又教育的方式呈现。
And it's only on Nebula, which you can get for free
我的纪录片独家发布在Nebula上，你可以
with Curiosity Stream.
通过Curiosity Stream免费观看。
Because Nebula is where I release all my videos early,
Nebula是我最先发布视频的地方，
usually with extended cuts and where I can experiment
通常我也会发布一些额外的剪辑，并且我还会做
with content and put things that I couldn't put on YouTube.
内容方面的实验和发布一些我无法发布到油管上的东西。
And we're thrilled to be partnering with today's sponsor
今天，我们非常开心能与Curiosity Stream赞助商
Curiosity Stream, because they're the go-to source
合作，因为他们是
for the best documentaries
全网观看最佳纪录片
and long form educational content on the internet.
和长篇教育内容的首选网站。
They even have an entire section
他们甚至还有一整部分内容
devoted to unsolved mysteries and crime.
是讲未解之谜和犯罪的。
So if you like my videos,
所以，如果您喜欢我的视频，
you will love the stuff on Curiosity Stream.
你也会喜欢Curiosity Stream上的内容。
And right now Curiosity Stream is offering
现在Curiosity Stream的年付费方案
42% off their annual plans.
提供42%的折扣。
That's less than $12 for the entire year
全年观看Curiosity Stream
for both Curiosity Stream and Nebula.
和Nebula不到12美元。
So if you click on the link in the description
如果你马上点击视频下方描述的链接
or the one that's on screen right now,
或者屏幕上的链接，
you'll get both Curiosity Stream and Nebula
您就能享受42%的折扣观看Curiosity Stream
for 42% off, or you can go to curiositystream.com/legal.
和Nebula，或者您也可以去curiositystream.com/legal。
It's a great way to support this channel
只需每年不到12美元就能很好
and educational content directly for under $12 per year.
的支持本频道和教育内容。
And it's the only way to see my documentary
并且这是唯一可以观看我纪录片的方式，
"Bad Law Words Good."
“法劣良词”。
So just click on the link that's on screen right now,
所以请立即点击屏幕上的链接，
or the one that's in the description
或者下方视频描述的链接
to get Curiosity Stream, Nebula and "Bad Law Words Good."
获取Curiosity Stream, Nebula和“法劣良词”。
Plus, clicking on that link really helps out this channel.
此外，点击那个链接真的可以帮助本频道。
And while you're there, click on this playlist
如果您还在，请点击这个播放列表
with all my other real law reviews.
观看我其他对真实案件的法律评鉴。
So click on that video or I'll see you in court.
请点击观看视频吧，否则咱们法庭上见。